recently we did a video I did a video
about aptitude aptitude ask you know
abilities skills and knowledge and the
question came in to Discord and and just
now uh
about what to do to assess your ability
for anything how are you going to do
your own assessment and fundamentally
the question is about self assessment
and that is its own video um you know do
you have an aptitude for something we
talked about what aptitude means in the
other video I'm not going to talk about
that to say aptitude is primarily you
know in my opinion you know that you
have a natural inate ability to do
something we talked about abilities
versus skills versus verus knowledge I'm
going to try really hard not to talk
about that um but so how do you assess
your abilities how do you assess your
aptitude how do you assess your skills
how do you assess your knowledge and in
in general how do you assess anything
and there's going to be at least one or
two people listening to this that are
say oh well obviously you need to like
take a test or get cert or certify it or
do something like that and that's not
wrong I think I think that uh the the
many many ways of assessment out there I
mean I'm I'm really I'm really avoiding
a huge Rabbit Hole here because
I mean there you
know there
entire books about assessment um and
there's huge debate about you know
whether a multiple choice test is the
true assessment of your skills and so
I'm just going to tell you what I think
as usual and then you can do your own
thing um
but I believe that it's largely like if
I I like imagining like a blacksmith
right where's the blacksmith right the
blacksmith and The Apprentice The
Apprentice
blacksmith um if you want to think of
Jedi fine uh but how did that how did
that relationship work and I think if we
dig into that relationship we'll we'll
kind of come to understand uh what it is
about um assessment that that actually
works and doesn't you know destroy your
soul and thing um and let's first talk
about the assessment that I think is the
most valuable and the kind that you
should do and get practice in your own
you know learning practice um and then
then we'll talk about all the other ones
and what I think is wrong with those
because it doesn't be negative but
whatever so I I think that the kind of
assessment that a a master blacksmith
would give to an apprentice blacksmith
is the right way to do it I think that's
it it's very real time uh you know it's
it's Project based you can imagine you
can imagine the you know the apprentice
and the master working together on a
project uh whatever it be from shooing a
horse to um you know to swords to kill
goblins or whatever you know it it you
could see the master and The Apprentice
working together as a team and you see
them the the one is honing their skills
and while the other one is is is
learning you know and and is practicing
and I think that's where the key is is
that it's the best assessment comes in
the in my opinion comes in the form of
realtime feedback about some actual
project that's the best assessment to me
um and and the the best you can get
period is to actually be doing something
together uh with somebody so like the
whole pod one you know Master idea
whether it's in martial arts or it's a
blacksmith you you're literally both
working on the same project and you're
both committed to do and not everybody's
going to be able to do that so that's
that's like a perfect world right a
perfect learning world would be somebody
who knows how to do the thing who's
literally employed doing whatever that
thing is uh maybe not but they've been
doing it their whole life and they are
available to literally do the thing with
you and to guide you like a tennis
lesson right and help you raise your
elbow you know or whatever you have to
do to to make the tiny minor micro
adjustments uh so that the assessment is
ongoing and constant and that is the
real key so the best true assessment is
ongoing and constant um now that I think
this is one of the areas where I think
AI is really really going to help us
because you know if if you're learning a
language for example right when you're
learning one of the reasons it's so
important to go into another country uh
or to immerse yourself in the culture of
that Lang and be around that culture
that language all the time and frankly
be around people who are very forgiving
uh this is going to sound weird but if
you're trying to learn that foreign
language which is got I'll do a separate
video on that um one of the best things
you can do is get to be friends with uh
young people um people who are not going
to judge you people who are going to
laugh and Snicker at your ability no
that's not how you say it's like this
right because when you're in that group
and you know learning how to speak a
foreign language uh it's the same way
whether you're a child or you're an
adult they you're getting constant
real-time feedback about your how you're
performing you know and when you fail
and you will obviously you're going to
fail a lot you get these micro failures
and you make these micro Corrections and
that is how the best learning happens in
my opinion it's the real time feedback
it's the ongoing immersion in what it is
you're learning and and it and it's
having that person looking over your
shoulder um or speaking to you right and
they'll correct you sometimes they'll
you know they'll do it nicely sometimes
they'll do it not so nicely so that that
is the best way for assessment that's
the best way for you to determine your
aptitude um and so so how do you take
the best form of assessment and and
apply that to deciding whether um
computer science is for you for example
um you know how could you assess whether
you have what it takes to be a computer
a technologist and that's kind of the
follow-up question to this is you know
how do you know and I told the story in
that other video very sad story about uh
a boy that I had been working with for
two years and uh in a very real you know
capacity you know watching him M make
micro changes and stuff um and he uh you
know eventually I had to let him go
because it was starting to kind of wear
on his soul and I told that story
elsewhere but but what how why that time
why why was that the day why was that
one day the day that that that finally
the assessment was it's probably time
for me to talk to your parents and have
them decide if you need to stay here or
you need to go you I didn't say that to
him um and it's a very fair question and
I I really don't have a direct answer to
it I think I think it was more of a feel
I was like it just felt like the right
time because because it may have been
triggered by one moment of particular
frustration he was having
and you know I was like just it was just
like one too many right and I was like
okay he's he's really frustrated it
wasn't that he sat down and had to take
a test and decide well how good he was
right and had I had could I have I mean
I I replay this entire failure in my
mind all the time is there something I
could have done upfront to you know weed
out uh somebody who doesn't have an
aptitude for computer science or or or
game deel or something is there could I
have decided could have discovered that
much earlier is there some way I could
have known even before we got his hopes
up and he got engaged into this whole
thing so that you know and I I don't
have the answer to that I honestly don't
I I don't have the answer to that I I
know that many countries have tried to
put gatekeeper assessments that don't
even let you into certain professions
you can't even get into certain schools
to educate yourself for certain
professions in certain countries unless
you pass a certain assessment and then
most that case it's usually a test you
can't even progress in your education
and in those in those countries if you
don't have a credential from one of
these institutions you can't do the job
and there's a separate video about why
certify and whether a credential is
required or not if you're you know if
you're a doctor the answer is yes if
you're you know a CEO the answer
strangely is no um so you know how do we
deal with all the ambiguities and touchy
feely you know assessment stuff well
Society has decided to clamp down on
this and say you have to pass this test
or you can't go on period you're not a
good test taker we don't care you you
you either know the stuff or you don't
and a lot of times the people that pass
the test don't know the stuff they just
know how to pass the test and I don't
believe that that is a true form of
assessment I want to see that kind of
assessment die in the world I hate it I
hate it I think it is a horrible idea uh
and I think people should generally
avoid uh test based assessment but you
can't there are so many ways that you
have to have this um so certificates are
a part of that but but more importantly
how do you know oh
gosh
that's that really scared me uh that
like legitimately scared me uh so there
there are going to be you could say that
g keep do a lot of Discovery where if
you start something and you find out you
enjoy it you'll put far more effort into
I agree I agree with that 100% um and
and so I think uh I mean this is a long
video but this is one of the more
important videos how do you assess
yourself and how how do you know when
you've assessed yourself enough to make
a definitive decision about whether you
want to do something or not and honestly
as I said before the answer is it's very
personal and every single person is
going to be different um you know and I
I don't I don't have a better answer for
you than that I really don't I wish I
could this is a very personal decision
deciding to go into technology um you
know but but just like anything in life
there is a certain level at which I mean
how many times did you change your major
right in college it's like have I really
sampled this career option and this path
enough I mean I changed my major from CS
CS computer science to Russian but did I
and actually I changed it from computer
science to French and then from French
to Russian right and I broke sh Thompson
the director of the French Department's
Hearts when I told her I was changing my
major over to Russian I mean she she she
gave me the most French look ever once I
told her that um It's actually kind of
the same dilemma right um had I given
French enough you know time to know
whether I wanted to go into it wasn't
that I was bad at it I just didn't want
to do it anymore I wanted to be a part
of the of the wall coming down and and
you know getting to know Russians and
everything and so I Chang my major to
Russia so there are a lot of I mean that
was more of an interest issue than an
aptitude issue but I can see people
having aptitude questions as well right
so oh oh here's a good one here's a good
one you'll love this one okay uh oh we
have an ad I'm so sorry um but but this
is a really good one okay so I thought I
wanted to be a physicist yeah you'll
like this story Rob failing miserably so
I I thought I had I had I had done
reports on black holes since I was 6
years old I had I I thought physics was
the coolest thing ever um I took all the
math that I needed to I mean seriously
from the time I was in the fifth grade I
was obsessed with black holes and with
physics and all of it and I thought that
I wanted to be a physicist in fact I
used to tell everybody I want to be a
physicist one day turns out I don't have
the chops to be a physicist so this is a
story about how I figured that out and
hopefully you can take something away
from this to help you decide whether you
spent enough time self-assessing in a in
computer science sence or technology or
something to decide you don't want to do
it so or you can't do it in this case um
I I remember sitting in physics 101
which very clearly is designed to
destroy your
soul you know I I don't this is one of
the things about academic educ like
formal Academia that I really hate
formal formal Academia will destroy your
um your soul they will deliberately put
in these gatekeeping weed out sessions
um and they will they will have it um
and that's what physics 101 is and so
physics 101 they there's an immense
amount of work and it's it's like story
problems on steroids it's like really
really hard to do and um you know I had
a really hard time with that I did I had
a really hard time with it I I couldn't
do it and I took physics in high school
as well I took AP Physics in high school
and I struggled struggled so hard it's
one of the few times when I literally
found myself in tears because I couldn't
get it no matter how much I thought I
could figure it out I couldn't get it
and I my I remember my that was one of
the few times my dad came down actually
helped me with homework because I mean I
was really messed up about it because it
was kind of like my dream was kind of
fading away from me I was not going to
be able to be a physicist and I couldn't
you know do these basic physics problem
even though my my AP Physics teacher was
you know salt to the earth guy was an
amazing human being
um he was also our counselor for the you
know executive Council and recommended
me to go to this leadership camp and all
kinds of stuff I mean but the the point
is is I sucked at physics I couldn't do
it I didn't have what it took
to I suppose visualize these story
problems which you know is pretty much
physics uh these days you put your chat
GPT yeah um and so anyway I but I I
still tried it I still tried it so I
took physics
101 uh my first year of college and um I
mean it crushed me man it crushed my
soul uh I didn't fail but I knew um I
knew that I was just not going to be
able to get it I I couldn't visualize
things I was too stuck in the pra it
turned out later I discovered much much
later that had I survived that and gone
into practical physics um so physics is
as you guys know there's there's
theoretical physics and then there's
practical physics practical physics
physicists are the people blowing stuff
up and and recording what happens and
they spend most of their days with you
know hard hats on doing crazy
experiments and and I was like damn I
wish someone had told me that if you
want a really good video on physics
watch particle uh fever it's really
amazing and it really goes into this
whole thing and you have the theoretical
physicist who have to set up all the
models and they spend the entire time in
front of a chalkboard uh trying to you
know with ungodly amounts of math skill
um and they they live in their heads
they don't they don't you know but they
need each other and had I known that
practical you know the Practical
physicist uh um was a thing I I probably
would have kept going with it had I had
I survive that class but but it was in
that class that I realized two things
and one of them is very inappropriate
and one of them is kind of on the point
the the the the valuable relevant thing
was I couldn't do I just didn't have the
knowledge and it wasn't going to happen
and the other thing I realized
was at least in this University all the
cute girls were in the French
Department give me a break I was 20 I
was like 19 and I was
unmarried that is such a horrible thing
to say that is such a horrible thing to
say I went to a Mormon University
okay I went to a Mormon University
this probably says more about it it was
okay it probably dude I okay this is
this is one of the times where you
know my hormones led me to make life
decisions I'm not kidding I am not
kidding I felt I felt Guided by the
spirit you know as like to to change my
major to a Humanity's major and it was
largely because I open the
door I I opened the door to the
Humanities Building and I walked into
the Humanities Building and I was like
what is happening here and I was like it
was like wall toall babes wall to- wall
you know college
babes I know I'm a shallow human being I
am so sorry I was 20 okay I was 19 or 20
or something also Mormon also you know a
virgin Civ it and all that Jaz so yeah I
I was I was guided to make it's like God
I think I should major in
French that's exactly what happened
confessions confessions with artifex Rob
I I had done physics and then I went to
CS one I went to computer science after
that I lasted one semester in computer
science it was the worst thing ever I
hated it it was not teaching me how to
code or make make games or anything it
wasn't doing anything important in the
world it was just sitting in front of a
computers with a bunch of boring people
listening to the te fight about C versus
Pascal and you know I hated it I hated
it I I hated it I fact I was like is
this computer science because if it is I
don't want to do anything you know what
as luck would have it in the humani lab
that's where all that practical
applications were being built they were
building software to teach people uh
languages and so I actually got a really
great practical education and and I
learned about the internet I learned
about uh how to how to administer PCS
and Max actually worked for the
Department I learned about uh uh Sound
Engineering because I work in the lab
there all because of the humanities
because of the humanity in order to
practice Humanities you have to use all
those Technologies uh how to write you
know hypercard and Flash and all that
jazz the macr media director I know AJ
myself and it was great I mean I was all
the I wanted to you know make things
with
applications uh with computers and stuff
I didn't really want to spend my time
you know dissecting bubble sorts oh my
God if you want to like force people out
of a technology career make them learn
how to do all the different sorting
algorithms the first time they have an
exposure to like actual computer science
it's horrible it's like if you don't
make the connection about what's
possible and the other thing too is you
think oh I can't do a bubble sword I
must be a horrible I'm not going to
pursue a Tech Career no you can do a
Tech Career you don't need to know all
that stuff I've talked talked a lot
about all that leak code stuff um you
know and and so it was but yeah so I
went you know I went into the humanties
building and my you know the spirit
spoke to me and said you should learn
languages and you should learn how to
use computers to help people learn
languages end up starting my own company
I started my own uh flash card uh
company I sold flashcards to the
bookstore Library I did a whole bunch of
stuff that I I learned a lot to
entrepreneurial skills um
uh yeah you got to know to quick swort
and and it was great and so this story
is this video is about assessing
yourself and knowing what your aptitude
is and knowing when uh to say no to
yourself and that that's not good um and
and that's a tough decision it's a very
personal decision you know people I
think a lot of people give up before
they give it a true a true test and I
think it's really scary this is why this
is such a hard topic right because and
this is one of the reasons I think it's
so important that you have a
mentor uh and it doesn't need to be me
it can be somebody from the industry I I
really you know what I that's a great
way to conclude this video I think the
answer to the question about
whether you've had enough right whether
you are good enough whether you are
going to suffer in that career or you're
not is for you to get a mentor who is in
the industry maybe maybe one or two of
them uh not a teacher who's going to
give you a test and you're going to fill
out the blanks and decide whether you
can do it or not you need to give you
need to find somebody who is in again
you need to Target this the job you want
we already talked about this you need to
Target you need to decide the skills you
want the the tasks you want to do every
day what do you want to actually what do
you enjoy doing then you need to isolate
the computer the jobs that are in that
area you need to Target a few companies
and then you need to find one or two
people to you who are specifically
either in those companies or in that job
and you can to pay them or not but you
need to get the feedback from those
people about what it is you're doing and
having that personal relationship like
the blacksmith that I talked about the
the best possible way to get real- time
assessment uh other than real time the
next best way is every week come back to
that mentor and say Here's the work I
did this week can you talk to me about
what I did and they're not going to give
you a grade they're going to say oh well
you might consider this here you might
consider this here and it could be art
it could be Sho horses it could be rust
for God's sake it doesn't matter
whatever it is you're going to make that
connection and the mentor is going to be
able to give you real-time feedback and
then and then when you come in you say
look this is feeling really hard to me
Mentor you say know I feel like this is
much harder than it should be is this
normal um you know and when that when
that uh sheo was just not otherwise yeah
they kind of are um and so the the the
point is is that you having the mentor
is going to be the the person who's got
your back who's going to help you stay
encouraged and say oh no everybody goes
through that that that part is always
hard this part is is is a thing you just
need to get through that and you'll be
fine right or you know I always remember
wax on wax off right I hate this I hate
wax on I always throw this video right
now go watch the wax on wax off video
it's one of the best videos ever Mr
Miyagi the Mr Miyagi and the Daniel
assoc relationship there is so classic
and it's a really good example of a
mentorship right because miyagi's like M
you know Mr miyagi's like you you watch
car wax on walks off that I mean he's
Japanese so horrible Japanese accent and
and Daniel's like my arm sore I've been
I've been washing your cars all day he's
like he's like he goes no this end time
he when you going to teach me to fight
and he's like I teach you in time he's
like that's [__] and he's like he
turns around he turns around to him I I
would show the video right now except I
get B make sure you go watch this video
it's so great Mr Magi turns to Daniel
and he says show show me wax on wax off
and he's like he goes go goes wax on wax
off goes show me S and show me and so
Daniel shows him the things he's been
practicing It's like got to be one of
the best scenes in all of history I
swear to God it's like one of the best
clip please make sure you go watch watch
it and and and then he goes now show and
and then he starts to attack him Mr
Biagi attacks Daniel and he uses wax on
wax off and sand the floor and
everything to block every attack from Mr
Miyagi and then Daniel's like oh whoa
and then Mr Miagi goes see you
tomorrow it's like it's such it's so
great I just love it you know why I love
it because Miyagi and Daniel don't have
any where near the same
personality you know what I mean they're
not they're totally from two different
totally different personality types but
yet Daniel Miyagi accepts him as a
mentor they have this mentorship
relationship and yeah and when he gets
frustrated you
know when he gets really frustrated when
Daniel gets frustrated miyagi's like no
this is a part of it let me show you and
he gives him the insight and then he
moves on and he gets past it and he goes
home and and and it's so funny the scene
of of Daniel walking away from the scene
he's like P practicing his Santa Flor
he's like he's like oh my God I just
learned like 15 new moves and I thought
I was just cleaning cars the whole time
so what does that have to do with
anything that that relationship is
really the only way I think that you're
going to be able to make a solid
confident decision about where you want
to go if you if you don't
have world if you if you don't have that
kind of input uh from a mentor you will
flounder and you will feel lost and you
like I don't know if I'm good enough you
know and having the mentor at first is a
way for you to help assess yourself now
I'm the last thing I'm going to say in
this video is that's not enough while I
do think it's good to have a mentor your
whole life um I think it's more
important that you learn over time to
self assess and I think that comes with
age honestly and or time and experience
but over time you'll start to feel when
it's time for you to give up and you
won't need a second party or somebody
you'll always need peerreview in a tech
world but you're you're going to get a
good sense of what you're good at and
what your superpowers are and and when
you're just struggling and when it's
really time to give it up right and I
think you're going to get a better sense
of that over time but at first I think
having a mentor and even even the even
the most experienced veterans still uh
will run something by and I do this all
the time one of the reasons I stream one
of the reasons I live stream is because
some of the things that I'm doing I'm
pushing my own boundaries and there are
people in my stream who are much more
experienced than I am who have done
amazing things and they'll come in and
they'll chime in and they'll help me out
sometimes in a nice way sometimes in a
horrible way um but but I'm able to get
that sort of reflection and get that
assessment and get the peer review which
which is not as fun as having a
dedicated Mentor in private to talk to
you talk to you about your personal
projects that's always best if you can
do that but if you can't do that you
know join a Discord group and put your
stuff out there um and have other people
comment on it and stuff there are people
that will do that so hopefully that's a
lot that's a lot but this is a this is
worth the time this particular topic is
worth the time so when do you know
whether you have an aptitude for
something and you should go for it